{
    "questions": [
        {
            "Question": "Which was the biggest building in Mohanjodaro?",
            "optionA": "  Great Bath ",
            "optionB": "  Granary ",
            "optionC": "  Huge Hall ",
            "optionD": "  Two Story Building ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGranary: A granary has been found which the largest building of the Mohenjo-Daro. ",
            "keyString": "248225s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Cereal(s) grown by the people of the Harappan Civilisation was/were",
            "optionA": "  Wheat ",
            "optionB": "  Rice ",
            "optionC": "  Millet ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWheat kind of bread was their staple, perhaps baked in ovens or cooked over fire. In some places, particularly Gujarat, they also cultivated some native millets; and possibly rice does not become an important crop until Post-Harappan times. ",
            "keyString": "248266s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statements about the Harappan people is incorrect?",
            "optionA": "  The Harappans were phallus worshippers ",
            "optionB": "  They worshipped gods in the form of human beings ",
            "optionC": "  They placed their gods in temples ",
            "optionD": "  They looked upon the earth as a fertility goddess ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHarappan people did not placed their gods in temples.",
            "keyString": "248281s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Harappan weapons were made of",
            "optionA": "  Stone ",
            "optionB": "  Copper ",
            "optionC": "  Bronze ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe main weapon of war and hunting used by Harappans were axe, spear, dagger, bow and arrow, mace, sling, sword, shield and armour. Most of them are of copper and Bronze. However mace was always made of stone. ",
            "keyString": "248293s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the correct chronology of the excavation of the site in the Indus civilization?\nI. Mohenjo-Daro\nII. Chanhudaro\nIII. Harappa\nIV. Lothal",
            "optionA": "  III, I, II & IV ",
            "optionB": "  I, III, II & IV ",
            "optionC": "  II, I, III & IV ",
            "optionD": "  III, IV, II & I ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe correct chronology of the excavation of the site in the Indus civilization are Harappa, Mohenjo-Daro, Chanhudaro, Lothal. ",
            "keyString": "248305s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the strength of Indus economy?",
            "optionA": "  Agriculture ",
            "optionB": "  Business ",
            "optionC": "  Pottery ",
            "optionD": "  Crockery ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCotton was one of the most important product of the Indus Valley trade. Their wealth was based on a subsistence economy of wheat and barley. Indus people were first to grow cotton in the world.",
            "keyString": "290507s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The language from which the term 'India' is derived is",
            "optionA": "  English ",
            "optionB": "  Greek ",
            "optionC": "  Persian ",
            "optionD": "  Arabic ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Persian 'Hindustan', and the Latin 'India', are both derived from the old-Persian term 'Hindu'. Hindu is Persian for Sindhu, the name for the Indus River in ancient Sanskrit. Hindustan became a commonly used term to refer to the Mughal Empire, comprising primarily of north India, prior to British rule. ",
            "keyString": "290577s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A prominent Harappan site, being surrounded by flood barriers in order to protect it with the aid of UNESCO funds, is",
            "optionA": "  Mohenjodaro ",
            "optionB": "  Dholavira ",
            "optionC": "  Lothal ",
            "optionD": "  Rakhigarhi ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMohenjodaro was the prominent Harappan site, being surrounded by flood barriers in order to protect it with the aid of UNESCO funds. ",
            "keyString": "290597s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following civilisations is not associated with the Harappan Civilisation?",
            "optionA": "  Mesopotamian ",
            "optionB": "  Egyptian ",
            "optionC": "  Sumerian ",
            "optionD": "  Chinese ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChinese civilisations is not associated with the Harappan Civilisation. ",
            "keyString": "290615s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Harappa is situated on the bank of the river",
            "optionA": "  Ganga ",
            "optionB": "  Ravi ",
            "optionC": "  Yamuna ",
            "optionD": "  Sindhu ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMohenjo-Daro or Mound of Dead is in 'Larkana\u201d district of Sind situated at the bank of river Indus. Harappa is situated in the Montgomery District of Punjab on the bank of river Ravi. ",
            "keyString": "290634s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In Indus Valley Civilization, Kalibangan is famous for which of the following?",
            "optionA": "  Rock cut architecture ",
            "optionB": "  Sea port ",
            "optionC": "  Cotton cultivation ",
            "optionD": "  Pottery ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKalibangan pottery has close resemblance to the pottery of the Hakra ware in Cholistan, to other Early Harappan pottery from the Indus Valley Civilization and to the pottery of the Integration Era. ",
            "keyString": "329817s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In Indus Valley Civilization, Dholavira is famous for which of the following?",
            "optionA": "  Rock cut architecture ",
            "optionB": "  Sea port ",
            "optionC": "  Water Conservation ",
            "optionD": "  Pottery ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDholavira is an archaeological site of immense importance to India as it is India's most prominent archaeological site associated with the Indus Valley Civilization. It represents the ruins of an ancient city of the Harappan civilization that was inhabited over a period of 1,200 years from 3000 BCE through 1800 BCE. It is famous for water conservation. ",
            "keyString": "329861s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The people of the Indus Valley Civilization usually built their houses of",
            "optionA": "  Burnt bricks ",
            "optionB": "  Stone ",
            "optionC": "  Wood ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHouses of Indus Valley Civilization were one or two stories high, made of baked (Pucca) bricks, with flat roofs. Each was built around a courtyard, with winddows overlooking the courtyard. The outside walls had no windows. Each home had its own private drinking well and its own private bathroom. Clay pipes led from the bathrooms to sewers located under the street. ",
            "keyString": "329876s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The economy of the Indus Valley people was based on?",
            "optionA": "  Agriculture ",
            "optionB": "  Trade and Commerce ",
            "optionC": "  Crafts ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTrade and Commerce. Intensive agricultural production and large-scale trade played significant roles in flourishing of the Harappan civilization. The elegant social structure and the standard of living must have been achieved by a highly developed system of communication and a strong economy. ",
            "keyString": "329889s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was not an Indus Valley site?",
            "optionA": "  Pataliputra ",
            "optionB": "  Rangpur ",
            "optionC": "  Sukatagendor ",
            "optionD": "  Lothal ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMajor sites in Pakistan of Harappan civilization are Harappa (on Ravi in W Punjab), Mohenjodaro (on Indus), Chanhu-Daro (on Sindh), etc. In India, major sites are Lothal, Rangpur and Surkotda (Gujarat), Kalibangan (Rajasthan), Banwali (Hissar), and Alamgirpur (Western UP). ",
            "keyString": "329901s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How were the streets of cities in Indus Valley Civilization?",
            "optionA": "  Wide and Straight ",
            "optionB": "  Narrowand Unhygienic ",
            "optionC": "  Slippery ",
            "optionD": "  Narrow and Curved ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe main streets were almost 10 metres wide - wide enough for two bullock carts or elephants to pass each other. ",
            "keyString": "391620s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Most of the large Harappan towns had for fortifications which served the purpose of",
            "optionA": "  safety from robbers ",
            "optionB": "  protection against cattle raiders ",
            "optionC": "  protection against floods ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe large Harappan towns had for fortifications which served the purpose of safety from robbers, protection against cattle raiders, protection against floods. ",
            "keyString": "391763s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following materials was mainly used in the manufacturing of Harappan seals?",
            "optionA": "  Terracotta ",
            "optionB": "  Bronze ",
            "optionC": "  Copper ",
            "optionD": "  Iron ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMost of the seals were made of steatite, which is a kind of soft stone. A few of them were also made of terracotta, gold, agate, chert, ivory and faience. The standard Harappan seal was square in shape with a 2X2 dimension. It is believed that the seals were used for commercial purposes.Most of the Harappan seals were made up of terracotta on which inscriptions and animals engrave on them. ",
            "keyString": "391810s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The town planning in the Harappan Civilisation was inspired by a regard for",
            "optionA": "  beauty and utility ",
            "optionB": "  uniformity ",
            "optionC": "  sanitation and public health ",
            "optionD": "  demographic factor ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Within the city, individual homes or groups of homes obtained water from wells. From a room that appears to have been set aside for bathing, waste water was directed to covered drains, which lined the major streets. Houses opened only to inner courtyards and smaller lanes. ",
            "keyString": "391843s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The people of Harappa and Mohenjo-Daro culture belonged to the",
            "optionA": "  New Stone Age ",
            "optionB": "  Copper Age ",
            "optionC": "  Iron Age ",
            "optionD": "  Chalcolithic Age ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indus or the Harappan civilisation belongs to the Chalcolithic or Bronze Age since the objects of copper and stone were found at the various sites of this civilisation. Nearly, 1,400 Harappan sites are known so far in the sub-continent. ",
            "keyString": "391873s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Harappan civilizations do not have homogeneity or uniformity in",
            "optionA": "  Weights and measures ",
            "optionB": "  Cereal crops ",
            "optionC": "  Burial practices ",
            "optionD": "  Both (B) and (C) ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn general, the burials in the Harappan period were all in brick or stone lined rectangular or oval pits. The body was usually interred clothed shrouded or in a wooden coffin in the north south direction in a straight direction. It was important that the body did not come into contact with the ground. The only evidence of wooden coffins is the presence of a wooden stain in the body of the corpse.",
            "keyString": "451242s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The local name of Mohenjodaro is",
            "optionA": "  Mound of the living ",
            "optionB": "  Mound of the tree ",
            "optionC": "  Mound of the dead ",
            "optionD": "  Mound of the survivor ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMohenjo-daro, the modern name for the site, has been variously interpreted as \"Mound of the Dead Men\" in Sindhi, and as \"Mound of Mohan\" (where Mohan is Krishna). ",
            "keyString": "451370s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which was the only city of the Indus without\nfortification?",
            "optionA": "  Kalibangan ",
            "optionB": "  Mohanjodaro ",
            "optionC": "  Harappa ",
            "optionD": "  Chanhudaro ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChanhu Daro is the only harappan city which does not have a fortified citadel. The Chanhu Daro has given evidence of factories of various figurines, seals, toys, bone implements so it has been interpreted that it was a settlement with lots of artisans and was an industrial town. ",
            "keyString": "451414s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following was common to both the Harappan society and the Rigvedic society?",
            "optionA": "  Horse ",
            "optionB": "  Female deities ",
            "optionC": "  Urban centres ",
            "optionD": "  Iron implements ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHorse was common to both the Harappan society and the Rigvedic society. ",
            "keyString": "451449s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following has not been found in the excavation of Harappan sites?",
            "optionA": "  Drains and well ",
            "optionB": "  Fort ",
            "optionC": "  Reservoirs ",
            "optionD": "  Temple with Shikhar ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNo temples have been excavated from the sites of Harappan Civilization. Harappan people used to worship 'Mother and Pashupati Maharaj. Yoni and Lingam worship culture was also prevalent in Harappa. ",
            "keyString": "451486s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The earliest city discovered in India was",
            "optionA": "  Harappa ",
            "optionB": "  Punjab ",
            "optionC": "  Mohenjo Daro ",
            "optionD": "  Sindh ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indus Valley Civilization has its earliest roots in cultures such as that of Mehrgarh, approximately 6000 BC. The two greatest cities, Mohenjo-daro and Harappa, emerged circa 2600 BC along the Indus River valley in Punjab and Sindh. ",
            "keyString": "507527s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Assertion (A): There is no conclusive proof of the presence of temples or public places of worship in the Indus civilization.\nReason (R): To the Harappans, religion was perhaps more a personal and a private matter than a public affair",
            "optionA": "  Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A ",
            "optionB": "  Both A and R are true but R is not a correct explanation of A ",
            "optionC": "  A is true but R is false ",
            "optionD": "  A is false but R is true ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indus Valley Civilization contained more than 1,000 cities and settlements. These cities contained well-organized wastewater drainage systems, trash collection systems, and possibly even public granaries and baths. Although there were large walls and citadels, there is no evidence of monuments, palaces, or temples. The uniformity of Harappan artifacts suggests some form of authority and governance to regulate seals, weights, and bricks. ",
            "keyString": "507559s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indus or Harappan Civilisation is distinguished from the other contemporary civilisations by its",
            "optionA": "  town planning ",
            "optionB": "  underground drainage system ",
            "optionC": "  uniformity of weights and measures ",
            "optionD": "  large agricultural surplus ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOne of the most remarkable features of the Indus valley civilization is that the city was provided with an excellent closed drainage system. Each house had its own drainage and soak pit which was connected to the public drainage. Brick laid channels flowed through every street. They were covered and had manholes at intervals for cleaning and clearing purposes. Large brick culverts with corbelled roofs were constructed on the outskirts of the city to carry excess water. Thus Indus people had a perfect underground drainage system. No other contemporary civilization gave so much attention to cleanliness. ",
            "keyString": "507574s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following Harappan sites is NOT located in Gujarat?",
            "optionA": "  Surkotada ",
            "optionB": "  Rangpur ",
            "optionC": "  Sutkagendor ",
            "optionD": "  Desalpur ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSutkagan Dor (or Sutkagen Dor) is the westernmost known archaeological site of the Indus Valley Civilization. It is located about 480 km west of Karachi on the Makran coast near Gwadar, close to the Iranian border, in Pakistan's Baluchistan Province. The site is near the western bank of the Dasht River and its confluence with a smaller stream, known as the Gajo Kaur. It was a smaller settlement with substantial stone walls and gateways. ",
            "keyString": "507587s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following Indus Valley sites is presently in Pakistan?",
            "optionA": "  Kalibangan ",
            "optionB": "  Harappa ",
            "optionC": "  Alamgirpur ",
            "optionD": "  Lothal ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t It is located in Punjab Province, Pakistan, on an old bank / bed of the River Ravi. ",
            "keyString": "507599s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following metal was not found in Harappan civilization?",
            "optionA": "  Gold ",
            "optionB": "  Copper ",
            "optionC": "  Silver ",
            "optionD": "  Iron ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Harappan civilisation never had a chance with this Red soil. This is the reason why Copper was used for almost all purpose, because it is available and Iron was not known to them because they are not exposed. ",
            "keyString": "575028s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following objects was not worshipped by the Indus valley people",
            "optionA": "  Mother Goddess ",
            "optionB": "  Pashupati Shiva ",
            "optionC": "  Trees such as Peepal and Acacia ",
            "optionD": "  Trimurti ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTrimurti was not worshipped by the Indus valley people. ",
            "keyString": "575061s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The harappan economy was primarily__________ in nature",
            "optionA": "  Rural ",
            "optionB": "  Industrial ",
            "optionC": "  Urban ",
            "optionD": "  Capitalist ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt is generally believed that economy of the Harappan people was mainly based on external trade. It is true to the extent that the Harappan urban centres were supported by the external trade but actually agriculture was the backbone of the civilization. ",
            "keyString": "575076s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following has not been found in the excavation in Terracotta of Indus Valley sites?",
            "optionA": "  Buffalo ",
            "optionB": "  Sheep ",
            "optionC": "  Cow ",
            "optionD": "  Pig ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCow has not been found in the excavation in Terracotta of Indus Valley sites. Cow was related to vedic culture not from Indus civilization.",
            "keyString": "575088s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Harappan site that had a dock is",
            "optionA": "  Alamgirpur ",
            "optionB": "  Harappa ",
            "optionC": "  Lothal ",
            "optionD": "  Mohenjo-Daro ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to the ASI, Lothal had the world's earliest known dock, which connected the city to an ancient course of the Sabarmati river on the trade route between Harappan cities in Sindh and the peninsula of Saurashtra when the surrounding Kutch desert of today was a part of the Arabian Sea. ",
            "keyString": "575100s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The granary discovered at Harappa was located",
            "optionA": "  Within the citadel at Mohenjodaro ",
            "optionB": "  In the \"Lower town' ",
            "optionC": "  Near the river Ravi ",
            "optionD": "  Beside the western gate of the city ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe so-called \"granary\" of Harappa is found on Mound F. It is a brick structure that was built on a massive brick foundation over 45 meters north south and 45 meters east- west. It was near the river Ravi. ",
            "keyString": "626408s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indus Valley Civilisation type was found in",
            "optionA": "  Sumer ",
            "optionB": "  Egypt ",
            "optionC": "  China ",
            "optionD": "  All the three ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe developments and features of the early civilizations of Mesopotamia (Sumer), Egypt, India (Indus River Valley, Harappa), China (Shang dynasty), and Mesoamerica (Olmec), starting from the creation of villages to the formation of civilizations. These civilizations appear to have developed in response to their environment and in reaction to their human need for survival and security. ",
            "keyString": "626445s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indus Valley Civilization has been assigned the period 2500-1800 BC on the basis of",
            "optionA": "  Mystical insight by modern seers ",
            "optionB": "  Markings on seals ",
            "optionC": "  Radio carbon dating ",
            "optionD": "  Travellers written accounts ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indus Valley Civilization has been assigned the period 2500-1800 BC on the basis of Radio carbon dating. ",
            "keyString": "626461s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The most common animal figure found at all the Harappan sites is",
            "optionA": "  unihorn bull ",
            "optionB": "  cow ",
            "optionC": "  bull ",
            "optionD": "  tiger ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe unihorn bull is a legendary creature that has been described since antiquity as a beast with a single large, pointed, spiraling horn projecting from its forehead. The unihorn bull was depicted in ancient seals of the Indus Valley Civilization and was mentioned by the ancient Greeks in accounts of natural history by various writers, including Ctesias, Strabo, Pliny the Younger, and Aelian. ",
            "keyString": "626475s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "One of the following Indus Valley site is in Pakistan",
            "optionA": "  Lothal ",
            "optionB": "  Kalibangan ",
            "optionC": "  Alamgirpur ",
            "optionD": "  Harappa ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indus Valley Civilisation was a Bronze Age civilisation mainly in the northwestern regions of the South Asia, extending from what today is northeast Afghanistan to Pakistan and northwest India.",
            "keyString": "626488s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who amongst the following is associated with the study of the Harappan Civilization?",
            "optionA": "  Charles Mason ",
            "optionB": "  Cunningham ",
            "optionC": "  M. Wheeler ",
            "optionD": "  M.S. Vats ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPandit Madho Sarup Vats (12 April 1896 \u2013 7 December 1955) was an Indian archaeologist and Sanskrit scholar who served as the Director-General of the Archaeological Survey of India (ASI) from 1950 to 1954. Pandit Vats is, especially, well known for his participation in the excavations at Mohenjodaro which he supervised from 1924. ",
            "keyString": "683374s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following scholars, who was the first to discover the Harappan Civilization?",
            "optionA": "  Sir Johan Marshall ",
            "optionB": "  R.",
            "optionC": " Banerjee ",
            "optionD": "  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHarappa was first discovered by Brittish archeologist Sir Alexander Cunningham during excavations in 1872. ",
            "keyString": "683406s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Harappan town considered to be a town of the artists and craftsmen was",
            "optionA": "  Mohenjo-Daro ",
            "optionB": "  Chanhudaro ",
            "optionC": "  Harappa ",
            "optionD": "  Lothalmenials ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChanhudaro is one of the most important sites of Indus Civilization. More than 2500 sites belonging to Indus Civilization are identified so far and Chanhudaro is one of the bigger sites where lot of scope is identified for excavation. However, of late, excavations in this site have not been in progress leading to a decline in contributions from this site. ",
            "keyString": "745773s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which was the backbone of Indus Economy?",
            "optionA": "  Agriculture ",
            "optionB": "  Trade ",
            "optionC": "  Wheel Made ",
            "optionD": "  Carpentry ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs in most other contemporary civilizations, agriculture was the backbone of the Indus economy. The people made extensive use of the wooden plows. Barley and wheat were the main food crops. Agriculture sustained the rudimentary urban centers that emerged. ",
            "keyString": "745806s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Harappans were the earliest people to produce",
            "optionA": "  Seals ",
            "optionB": "  Bronze implements ",
            "optionC": "  Cotton ",
            "optionD": "  Barely ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFarmers in the Indus valley were the first to spin and weave cotton. In 1929 archaeologists recovered fragments of cotton textiles at Mohenjo-Daro, in what is now Pakistan, dating to between 3250 and 2750 BCE. Cottonseeds founds at nearby Mehrgarh have been dated to 5000 BCE. Literary references further point to the ancient nature of the subcontinent's cotton industry. The Vedic scriptures, composed between 1500 and 1200 BCE allude to cotton spinning and weaving. ",
            "keyString": "745822s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is the excavator of Harappa site?",
            "optionA": "  Daya ram sahni ",
            "optionB": "  Rakhal das Bannerji ",
            "optionC": "  Mackey ",
            "optionD": "  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first extensive excavations at Harappa were started by Rai Bahadur Daya Ram Sahni in 1920. ",
            "keyString": "745834s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Great bath was found at",
            "optionA": "  Harappa ",
            "optionB": "  Lothal ",
            "optionC": "  Chanhudaro ",
            "optionD": "  Mohanjodaro ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Great Bath is one of the best-known structures among the ruins of the ancient Indus Valley Civilization at Mohenjo-daro in Sindh, Pakistan. ",
            "keyString": "745847s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "At which Indus Valley site the Dockyard was found?",
            "optionA": "  Lothal ",
            "optionB": "  Ropar ",
            "optionC": "  Kalibangan ",
            "optionD": "  Banawali ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Lothal had the world's earliest known dock, which connected the city to an ancient course of the Sabarmati river on the trade route between Harappan cities in Sindh and the peninsula of Saurashtra when the surrounding Kutch desert of today was a part of the Arabian Sea. ",
            "keyString": "791075s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The worship of Mother goddess was related",
            "optionA": "  With the Aryan Civilization ",
            "optionB": "  With the Mediterranean Civilization ",
            "optionC": "  With the Indus Valley Civilization ",
            "optionD": "  With the Vedic Civilization ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe recovery of a large number of Mother Goddess figurines almost from every excavated site suggests that the Mother Goddess worship cult was very wide-spread during Indus days. The figurine has been cast with an elaborate headgear supported by a pair of bands and a brooch, tight-fitted short tunic with skirt part fastened with a broad waist-band using a medallion like clasp, and tight-fitted trousers, necklaces, ear-ornaments.",
            "keyString": "862501s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following animals was not known to the people of Indus Valley Civilisation?",
            "optionA": "  Horse ",
            "optionB": "  Cow ",
            "optionC": "  Giraffe ",
            "optionD": "  Elephant ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGiraffe was not known to the people of Indus Valley Civilisation. ",
            "keyString": "862534s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Whose statue was an important creation of the people of Indus Valley Civilization?",
            "optionA": "  Natraj ",
            "optionB": "  Dancing Girl ",
            "optionC": "  Buddha ",
            "optionD": "  Narasimha ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDancing Girl is a prehistoric bronze sculpture made in approximately 2500 BCE in the Indus Valley Civilisation city of Mohenjo-daro (in modern-day Pakistan), which was one of the earliest human cities. The Girl was in dancing position and was wearing a no. of bangles in her both hands ",
            "keyString": "862548s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the script of Indus Valley Civilization?",
            "optionA": "  Tamil ",
            "optionB": "  Kharshthi ",
            "optionC": "  Unknown ",
            "optionD": "  Brahmi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt is not Known.Seals found during excavation of Indus Valley Civilization had symbolic (pictographic) script which has not been deciphered yet.The Indus script (also known as the Harappan script) is a corpus of symbols produced by the Indus Valley Civilisation during the Kot Diji and Mature Harappan periods between 3500 and 1900 BCE. ",
            "keyString": "862560s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Of the following scholars who was the first to discover the traces of the Harappan Civilisation?",
            "optionA": "  Sir John Marshall ",
            "optionB": "  RD Banerji ",
            "optionC": "  A Cunningham ",
            "optionD": "  Daya Ram Sahani ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHarappa was first discovered by Brittish archaeologist Sir Alexander Cunningham during excavations in 1872. ",
            "keyString": "862572s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Harappan Civilisation achieved far greater advancement than Sumer, Elam etc. on account of its",
            "optionA": "  town planning ",
            "optionB": "  metal working ",
            "optionC": "  weights and measures ",
            "optionD": "  seals and figures ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe town-planning of Harappan culture is one of its most impressive aspects, as though it was the handiwork of a genius of an architect. Immaculate was the arrangement of the city. In every aspect like roads, houses, drainage, bath, granary, the Harappan people have left an imprint of originality and brilliance. ",
            "keyString": "974300s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many layers of Mohenjo-daro were found?",
            "optionA": "  6 ",
            "optionB": "  7 ",
            "optionC": "  8 ",
            "optionD": "  9 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t7 layers of Mohenjo-daro were found. ",
            "keyString": "974333s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Harappan Civilisation declined as a result of",
            "optionA": "  Aryan invasion ",
            "optionB": "  Decline in foreign trade ",
            "optionC": "  Ecological factors ",
            "optionD": "  Not definitely known factors ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Though the reason of the decline is not known, but through excavations it is clear that fall of the Harappan Civilization occurred between 1800 BC to 1700 BC. It is commonly believed that the Aryans were the next settlers. ",
            "keyString": "974348s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "After the partition of India, the largest number of Harappan towns and settlements have been found In",
            "optionA": "  Punjab ",
            "optionB": "  Haryana ",
            "optionC": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionD": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t After the partition of India, the largest number of Harappan towns and settlements have been found in Gujarat. ",
            "keyString": "974360s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Harappan or Indus Valley Civilisation flourished during the __________ age",
            "optionA": "  Megalithic ",
            "optionB": "  Paleolithic ",
            "optionC": "  Neolithic ",
            "optionD": "  Chalcolithic ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChalcolithic, which means the copper-stone phase. The Chalcolithic cultures followed the Bronze Age Harappa culture. ",
            "keyString": "974371s57m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The people of the Indus Valley civilization worshipped __________",
            "optionA": "  Vishnu ",
            "optionB": "  Pashupati ",
            "optionC": "  Indra ",
            "optionD": "  Brahma ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe deity Shiva Pashupati have been found on clay seals unearthed. Pashupati Madeva was the chief male diety of people of Indus valley civilization. The Pashupati seal found at Mohanjodaro has an image of Pashupati Mahadeva with three face, two horns, sitting on a low throne. He is surrounded by a tiger, a rhino, a buffalo,and an elephant, with two deers near his feet. ",
            "keyString": "26735s58m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mohenjo-Daro is situated in",
            "optionA": "  Montgomery district ",
            "optionB": "  Larkana district ",
            "optionC": "  Chandigarh area ",
            "optionD": "  Gujarat ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMohenjo-daro is located west of the Indus River in Larkana District, Sindh, Pakistan, in a central position between the Indus River and the Ghaggar-Hakra River. It is situated on a Pleistocene ridge in the middle of the flood plain of the Indus River Valley, around 28 kilometres (17 mi) from the town of Larkana. ",
            "keyString": "26769s58m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Name the oldest civilization",
            "optionA": "  Indus Valley civilization ",
            "optionB": "  Mesopotamian civlization ",
            "optionC": "  Egyptian civilization ",
            "optionD": "  Chandragupta Vikramaditya ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWe believe Sumerian civilization first took form in southern Mesopotamia around 4000 BCE\u2014or 6000 years ago\u2014which would make it the first urban civilization in the region. Mesopotamians are noted for developing one of the first written scripts around 3000 BCE: wedge-shaped marks pressed into clay tablets. ",
            "keyString": "26782s58m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Indus Valley civilisation can be said to belong to the",
            "optionA": "  Paleolithic age ",
            "optionB": "  Primitive age ",
            "optionC": "  Neolithic age ",
            "optionD": "  Bronze age ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indus Valley Civilisation (IVC) was a Bronze Age civilisation (3300\u20131300 BCE; mature period 2600\u20131600 BCE) mainly in the northwestern regions of the South Asia, extending from what today is northeast Afghanistan to Pakistan and northwest India. ",
            "keyString": "26795s58m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which was the only Indus city without a citadel?",
            "optionA": "  Kalibangan ",
            "optionB": "  Harappa ",
            "optionC": "  Mohenjodaro ",
            "optionD": "  Chanhudaro ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChanhudaro is an archaeological site belonging to the post-urban Jhukar phase of Indus valley civilization. It was the only Indus city without a citadel. ",
            "keyString": "26807s58m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The date of the Harappan Civilisation (2300-1750 BC) has been fixed on the basis of",
            "optionA": "  Pottery design ",
            "optionB": "  Stratification ",
            "optionC": "  Aryan invasion ",
            "optionD": "  Radio Carbon-14 dating ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRecently Indian archeologists using the technique of radio carbon dating, are inclined to believe that the period of Harappan culture extended from 2500 B.C. to 1500 B.C. ",
            "keyString": "96741s58m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first metal used by man was",
            "optionA": "  Aluminium ",
            "optionB": "  Copper ",
            "optionC": "  Iron ",
            "optionD": "  Silver ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFirst metal used by man was Copper (Cu).The popularity of gold is largely due to its scarcity, value and mankind's fascination with the metal. Copper, 4200BC - The use of copper in antiquity is of more significance than gold as the first tools, implements and weapons were made from copper. ",
            "keyString": "96774s58m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Ruins of Harappa and Mohanjodaro were found on which of the following river bank?",
            "optionA": "  Ravi ",
            "optionB": "  Indus ",
            "optionC": "  Beas ",
            "optionD": "  A and B both ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Ruins of Harappa and Mohanjodaro were found on river Ravi and Indus. Mohenjodaro was located the west of Indus river in Sindh, Pakistan. City of Harappan was located near the ravi river, in Punjab, Pakistan. ",
            "keyString": "96788s58m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Kalibangan is situated in",
            "optionA": "  Uttar Pradesh ",
            "optionB": "  Sindh ",
            "optionC": "  Rajasthan ",
            "optionD": "  Gujarat ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKalibangan is a town located at southern banks of the Ghaggar (Ghaggar-Hakra River) in Tehsil Pilibangan, between Suratgarh and Hanumangarh in Hanumangarh District, Rajasthan, India 205 km. from Bikaner. It is also identified as being established in the triangle of land at the confluence of Drishadvati and Sarasvati Rivers. ",
            "keyString": "96800s58m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The utensils of the Indus Valley people were mainly made of",
            "optionA": "  clay ",
            "optionB": "  copper ",
            "optionC": "  bronze ",
            "optionD": "  brass ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe utensils of the Indus Valley people were mainly made of clay. Clay pots were made and used for cooking purpose, and various other utensils were also made of clay. ",
            "keyString": "96812s58m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What were the crops raised by the Harappans?\nI. Cotton\nII. Wheat \nIII. Barley \nIV. Peas\nSelect the correct option",
            "optionA": "  I, II, III and IV ",
            "optionB": "  I, II and III ",
            "optionC": "  II, III and IV ",
            "optionD": "  II and III ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe types of crops that the Indus Civilization had was wheat, barley, peas, lentils, linseed, and mustard. Experts say that they might have grown cotton in the summer. They did not grow rice because it didn't grow well where they lived, but they did find white rice and fed it to their animals. ",
            "keyString": "152986s58m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The famous Harappan site of Lothal is situated in",
            "optionA": "  Sind ",
            "optionB": "  Rajasthan ",
            "optionC": "  Gujarat ",
            "optionD": "  Maharashtra ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLothal situated in Gujarat was excavated by S.R.Rao in the year 1957. This town of Indus Valley Civilisation is located on the bank of river Bhagava in Gujarat. The city located beside a tributary of the Sabarmati, in Gujarat which is close to the Gulf of Khambat. ",
            "keyString": "153024s58m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of all Harappan sites,  has the most impressive drainage system?",
            "optionA": "  Harappa ",
            "optionB": "  Banawali ",
            "optionC": "  Dhaulavira ",
            "optionD": "  Mohenjodaro ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe most striking feature of this Harappan civilization (Indus Valley Civilization) is that the Indus Valley people had constructed their drainage system on very scientific lines. The drainage system of Mohen-jo-daro is so elaborate that \u201cthe like of which has not yet been found anywhere in the world in any other city of the same antiquity\". ",
            "keyString": "153039s58m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "At which of the following Harappan sites has a supposed dockyard been found?",
            "optionA": "  Kalibangan ",
            "optionB": "  Lothal ",
            "optionC": "  Suktagendor ",
            "optionD": "  Sotka Koli ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe dominant sight at Lothal is the massive dockyard which has helped make this place so important to international archaeology. ",
            "keyString": "153052s58m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following domesticated animals was absent in the terracottas of the Indus civilization?",
            "optionA": "  Buffalo ",
            "optionB": "  Sheep ",
            "optionC": "  Cow ",
            "optionD": "  Pig ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCow was absent in the terracottas of the Indus civilization. The terracotta figurines excavated at Harappan site had images of oxen, buffaloes, pigs, goat, sheep and humpes bull. Cow was famous in vedic culture. ",
            "keyString": "153063s58m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The script of the Indus Valley Civilization was",
            "optionA": "  Dravidian ",
            "optionB": "  Persian ",
            "optionC": "  Sanskrit ",
            "optionD": "  Undecipherable ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPeople living in Harappa or Mohenjo-daro today are even more likely to be the inheritors of that civilization. The key to the Indus script linguistically is Dravidian, then culturally the key to the Indus script is Vedic. ",
            "keyString": "206116s58m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The archaeologist to initially discover the Mohenjo-Daro site of the Indus Valley Civilization was",
            "optionA": "  Sir John Marshall ",
            "optionB": "  Daya Ram Sahni ",
            "optionC": "  Sir Martimir Wheeler ",
            "optionD": "  Rakhal Das Banerji ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBanerji (also known as Rakhal das Banerjee and Rakhaldas Bandyopadhyay) was working for the Archaeological Survey of India in 1920, surveying the lower part of the Indus River valley (now part of Pakistan), when he heard reports of a buried site surmounted by a stupa, a small hemispherical structure used by Buddhist monks for meditation. ",
            "keyString": "206147s58m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The striking feature of the Indus Valley Civilization was",
            "optionA": "  Urban Civilization ",
            "optionB": "  Agrarian Civilization ",
            "optionC": "  Mesolithic Civilization ",
            "optionD": "  Paleolithic Civilization ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndus civilization, also called Indus valley civilization or Harappan civilization, the earliest known urban culture of the Indian subcontinent. The striking feature of the Indus Valley Civilization was Urban Civilization. ",
            "keyString": "206161s58m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The essential feature of the Indus Valley Civilization was",
            "optionA": "  Worship of forces of nature ",
            "optionB": "  Organised city life ",
            "optionC": "  Pastoral farming ",
            "optionD": "  Caste society ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere was a sophisticated concept of town planning in the Indus Valley Civilization. From excavations we get to to know that there was flourishing urban architecture. Some of the features are listed below: Grid Pattern Harappa and Mohen-Jo Dero were laid out on a grid pattern and had provisions for an advanced drainage system. Streets were oriented east to west. Each street was having a well organized drainage system. City Walls Each city in the Indus Valley was surrounded by massive walls and gateways. The walls were built to control trade and also to stop the city from being flooded. Each part of the city was made up of walled sections. The acropolis and the lower cities. A typical city would be divided into two sections, each fortified separately. One section was located on an artificially raised mound (sometimes called acropolis) while the other level was on level ground. ",
            "keyString": "206173s58m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Most depicted animal of the Indus Valley Civilization was?",
            "optionA": "  Elephant ",
            "optionB": "  Lion ",
            "optionC": "  Bull ",
            "optionD": "  Dog ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBull seal, Harappa. The majestic zebu bull, with its heavy dewlap and wide curving horns is perhaps the most impressive motif found on the Indus seals. Most depicted animal of the Indus Valley Civilization was Bull. ",
            "keyString": "206185s58m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Great Bath of Indus Valley civilisation is found at",
            "optionA": "  Harappa ",
            "optionB": "  Mohenjo-Daro ",
            "optionC": "  Ropar ",
            "optionD": "  Kalibangan ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Great Bath is one of the best-known structures among the ruins of the ancient Indus Valley Civilization at Mohenjo-daro in Sindh, Pakistan. Archaeological evidence indicates that the Great Bath was built in the 3rd millennium BCE, soon after the raising of the \"citadel\" mound on which it is located. ",
            "keyString": "254271s58m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Social System of the Harappans was",
            "optionA": "  Fairly egalitarian ",
            "optionB": "  Slave Labour based ",
            "optionC": "  Colour Varna based ",
            "optionD": "  Caste based ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t The Social System of Harappans was fairly egalitarian (equality and equal rights). The archaeological record of the Indus civilization provides practically no evidence of armies, kings, slaves, social conflict, prisons, and other oft-negative traits that we traditionally associated with early civilizations. If there were neither slaves nor kings, a more egalitarian system of governance may have been practiced. ",
            "keyString": "254309s58m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which was the only Indus site with an artificial brick dockyard?",
            "optionA": "  Lothal ",
            "optionB": "  Kalibangan ",
            "optionC": "  Harappa ",
            "optionD": "  Mohenjo Daro ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLothal was the port city of Indus Valley Civilization. It was located at Saragwala, Gujarat. The dockyard was located away from the main current to avoid deposition of silt. It is speculated that Lothal engineers studied tidal movements, and their effects on brick-built structures, since the walls are of kiln-burnt bricks. ",
            "keyString": "254331s58m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which statement on the Harappan Civilization is correct?",
            "optionA": "  Horse sacrifice was known to them ",
            "optionB": "  Cow was sacred to them ",
            "optionC": "  Pashupati' was venerated by them ",
            "optionD": "  The culture was generally static ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Pashupati Seal is a steatite seal that was discovered at the Mohenjo-daro archaeological site of the Indus Valley Civilization. The seal depicts a seated figure that is possibly tricephalic (having three heads). It was once thought to be ithyphallic, an interpretation that is now mostly discarded.",
            "keyString": "254349s58m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Harappans did not know the use of",
            "optionA": "  Copper ",
            "optionB": "  Bronze ",
            "optionC": "  Gold ",
            "optionD": "  Iron ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIron was not used in the the Harappan cities. Harappan cities are the part of Indus Valley Civilisation, which was held after the Chalcolithic period of stone age. During the Chalcolithic period copper was first used to make tools, utensils and other objects. ",
            "keyString": "254365s58m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "There are similarities between the seals found at Mohenjo-Daro and __________",
            "optionA": "  Egypt ",
            "optionB": "  China ",
            "optionC": "  Sumeria ",
            "optionD": "  Afghanistan ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOne seal from Mohenjo-daro shows a half-human, half-buffalo monster attacking a tiger. This may be a reference to the Sumerian myth of a monster created by Aruru\u2014the Sumerian earth and fertility goddess\u2014to fight Gilgamesh, the hero of an ancient Mesopotamian epic poem. This is a further suggestion of international trade in Harappan culture. ",
            "keyString": "292863s58m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What was the time period of Indus Civilization / Harappan Civilization?",
            "optionA": "  2400 BC - 1700 BC ",
            "optionB": "  2500 BC - 1700 BC ",
            "optionC": "  2400 BC - 1750 BC ",
            "optionD": "  2500 BC - 1750 BC ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Indus Valley Civilization (IVC) was a Bronze Age civilization (3300-1300 BCE; mature period 2600-1900 BCE) extending from what today is northeast Afghanistan to Pakistan and northwest India. ",
            "keyString": "292894s58m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The organic relationship between the ancient culture of the Indus Valley and Hinduism of today is proved by the worship of",
            "optionA": "  Pashupati, Indra and the Mother Goddess ",
            "optionB": "  Stones, trees and animals ",
            "optionC": "  Vishnu and Lakshmi ",
            "optionD": "  Siva and Sakti ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere has been evidence that the people of the Indus Valley Civilization believed in some form of animal, stone and nature worship.",
            "keyString": "292908s58m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Out of the following remains excavated in Indus Valley, which one indicates the commercial and economic development?",
            "optionA": "  The Pottery ",
            "optionB": "  Seals ",
            "optionC": "  The boats ",
            "optionD": "  The houses ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe seals were pressed into soft clay to seal the mouths of jars and, as suggested by the imprint of fabric on the back of some seal impressions, were used to create clay tags for sacks of traded goods such as grain. Indus Valley seals have been found as far afield as Mesopotamia (present-day Iraq) in the cities of Umma and Ur, in Central Asia and on the coast of the Arabian Peninsula. A large number of seals have been found at the port of Lothal in western India. Finds of Mesopotamian weights in Indus Valley cities confirm that trading took place between these two civilisations. Some experts believe that Mesopotamian written records of trade in gold, copper and jewellery may be referring to the Indus Valley. ",
            "keyString": "292920s58m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Harappas had commercial relations with __________",
            "optionA": "  China ",
            "optionB": "  Jawa ",
            "optionC": "  Mesopotamia ",
            "optionD": "  Burma (Now, Myanmar) ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe trade relationship during the later 3rd millennium was a direct one: ships from Meluhha (the Indus) docked in Mesopotamian ports; some Meluhhans settled in Sumer; and there is a seal belonging to a Mesopotamian whose job it was to act as an interpreter of the Meluhhan language. On the other hand, there is nothing to suggest that people from Mesopotamia reached the Indus, so it is clear that the Harappans conducted the trade between the two civilizations. Mesopotamian ships sailed the length of the Gulf, as far as the western coast of Magan (Oman peninsula), trading directly with Magan and with Dilmun (Bahrain); ships from Magan and Dilmun also docked in Mesopotamian ports.",
            "keyString": "292931s58m14h11d13m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        }
    ]
}